[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome back
to EnglishPod. My name is Marco.
My name is Catherine
and today we have an
upper intermediate
level lesson for all of you.
That's right, we're going
to be talking business
on this occasion on
EnglishPod but specifically
about planning a
business. Right, so before a
business opens, a lot of
planning has to happen,
that means people will
decide what kind of product
they want to sell, what
kind of a market they
want to sell to, etc.
So that is the focus of
today's lesson, let's take
a listen to the dialogue
for the first time and we'll be back in
a minute to talk about what's going on.
I've had it. I'm done
working for a company that
is taking me nowhere. So
what are you going to do?
Just quit? That's exactly what I'm going to
do. I've decided to create my own company.
I'm going to write
up a business plan, get
some investors and
start working for myself.
Have you ever written
up a business plan before?
Well, no. It can't be that hard.
I mean, all you have to
do is explain your business.
How are you going to do
things and that's it, right?
You can be more wrong.
A well-written business
panel will include an
executive summary which
highlights the idea of the
business in two pages or less.
Then you need to
describe your company
with information such as what type
of legal structure it has, history, etc.
Well, that seems easy
enough. Wait, there's more.
Then you need to
introduce and describe your
goods or services. What
they are and how they're
different from competitors.
Then comes the hard part,
a market analysis. You
need to investigate and
analyze hundreds of
variables. You need to take
into consideration
socio-economic factors from
GDP per capita to how
many children on average
the population has. All
this information is useful
so that you can move
on to your strategy and
implementation stage
where you will describe in
detail how you will
actually execute your idea.
Jeez, is that all? Almost.
The most important
piece of information
for your investors
will be the financial
analysis. Here you will
calculate and estimate
sales, cash flow and profits.
After all, people will
want to know when they
will begin to see a
return on their investment.
I think I'll just stick to my
old job and save myself
all the hassle of trying
to start up a business.
All right, we're back. So
the guy wanted to open
up a business, but his
friend explained that
it's not so easy and
gave a lot of interesting
words and phrases there. He
did. He seemed a little naive.
Like, he didn't really know how much
work is involved in opening a business.
Exactly. So I think we
should take a look at
some of the words used
on language takeaway.
Language takeaway. The
first word is the heart and
soul of the process
before you open a business.
It's the business plan.
All right. So the business
plan, as you said, it's a
noun and it's basically
a document that explains
what's going on in the business.
Exactly. It's a paper that you write
about the business that you want to open.
And it's a plan. So as the name
says, you have to tell what you
will do, how much money
you will spend, how much
money you will need.
You know, because if you're
asking people for money,
they want to know where
the money will be
spent. If it's going to be
spent on wise decisions.
Exactly. And as you mentioned,
so you show this business
plan maybe to a bank,
but also maybe to an
investor. That's right.
So investor is our next
word. It's another noun,
but this noun is a person.
A person is an investor.
If he or she gives money to someone else
and expects more money to come back, right.
So a person that's starting out
a business maybe has enough
money himself to open up
a business. But sometimes
you need extra money.
So you look for investors,
people who are interested
in giving you money.
For example, I have a
cupcake company. I want to sell
cupcakes to people. And
I need a thousand dollars.
So Marco, do you
want to be an investor?
Do you want to invest
someone? Yes, for sure.
Cupcake company. That sounds
great. I know. But what happens
if I don't sell cupcakes?
That's a problem for
you because you have
made a risky investment.
That's right. So that's what
happens with investors.
But now if you want
to attract the attention
of your investors with
your business plan, I
think part of the most
important aspects of this
plan is the executive
summary. A summary is usually
an outline of the important
points of a paper or document.
So in this case, I
could say, Catherine's
cupcake company will
sell delicious cupcakes
of 10 different flavors
to the market of
five-year-olds to 55-year-olds.
People will love them.
She has a great secret recipe. And she plans
to triple her investments by next year.
Right. That's exactly
it. So if an investor
reads the executive
summary, which shouldn't be
more than two pages long,
you can pretty much get
the idea of what
the business is about.
So if you want more details,
you have to read the rest of
the business plan. But
mainly with the executive
summary, you can more or
less know what it's all about.
Exactly. So a summary, like I said, is
something that should be short and it should
give you all of the most important
information about something.
Exactly. And well, they were talking more
in depth about, you know, analyzing things
and doing some research.
And among those things,
the girl mentioned it's
the social economic factors.
Okay. When I said we're going to sell
cupcakes for my company to people between the
ages of five and 55, we
need to analyze, we need
to look at those, they're
socioeconomic factors.
Socio comes from the word
social. It means we're in society.
They are their upper class, middle class
or lower class. Economic means how much
money do they make? Do
they make $10,000 a year or
$100,000 a year? And
so the kind of people we
want to sell my cupcakes
to will be, will change
according to their
socio economic factors.
That's right. So as you
mentioned, socio comes from the
word social or from
society. So you're analyzing
these factors from society.
And well, part of these
factors is the GDP per capita. So we have
two different words there in acronym GDP.
GDP gross domestic products.
Okay. That might seem confusing
because gross means different
things at different times.
But in this case, domestic
means our country.
So within a country,
all of the products
added up together.
Right. And gross is basically
that just all the products
added up together
without taking into
consideration any other things.
So the GDP is basically
all the goods and
services produced in a
country within a given time.
And what about
per capita though?
So per capita comes from a
Latin per means four or each.
And capital is ahead.
So this is per person.
So GDP per capita means
how much how many goods
and services are made
divided by the number of
people in that place?
Exactly. So you probably
have these indicators in
your country or your own
language as well.
But that's basically it.
And the acronym is
gross domestic product.
And just to explain a little
bit, if you see this in Wikipedia
or in an encyclopedia,
normally a very low GDP
per capita is $500
American dollars and a high
one would be $35,000. And
that's usually per year, right?
Because that's usually how
it's taken into consideration.
The time is a year. All right.
So those are the words
that we have for you on
language takeaway. Now,
why don't we move on to a
couple of different
phrases on fluency builder?
Fluency builder. Okay.
So this is important.
First phrase Marco has to
do with our last first phrase.
We had a business
plan. So what do you do?
You write up a
business plan. Right.
And that's a common way
of saying to write or to create,
to work on a business
plan, to write up. Right.
So it's something that we say that's very
colloquial, something that is very spoken.
And I can't explain why we say
it. But you'll sound very fluent.
If you say, I'm
going to write up a
business plan or why don't
you write up a business plan?
Right. So it would
be correct to say, I'm
going to write a business
plan or I have to write
a business plan. But if you use this phrase,
I'm going to write up a business plan.
It's just, it's more fluent. Right.
It's just more native like exactly.
All right. And our next phrase
is a return on investment. Okay.
So early we talked about
investors. The money that they invest
is called an investment.
Okay. These words are all
very closely related. And
when Marco decided to
give money to my cupcake
business, he expects the
money to come back and
he expects more actually
to come back than what
he put in. So that's called
a return on investment, the
money that's the difference.
So if he gives me
a thousand dollars
and I give him back $1,500
in a year, he made $500.
That's amazing. That means it's
a good return on his investment.
Right. So that's the term that
we use a return on investment to.
So you don't say to return on
investment. You see a return on investment.
Exactly. It's a
thing. It's a number.
It's a quantity. It's
something you can count.
Right. And well, in the
end, after seeing that
this business plan does
not so easy, the guy
said, "You know what? I'm not going to quit
my job and just save myself the hassle.
" What's the hassle? The
hassle. That's an interesting word.
So if I'm going to
save myself the hassle,
the hassle is like the
problem or the hard
work that it involves.
It's a lot of trouble.
A lot of trouble. So I
was going to cook some
dinner tonight, but
I'm going to save myself
the hassle of going to
the grocery store and
buying it and cooking
it by just ordering food.
Right. So that's a good
example. Instead of doing
all the work of cooking,
you just save yourself
the hassle, pick up the phone and
get food delivered to your house.
Right. And the word
we change here,
you can say, "Save myself, save yourself,
save his self." So you change that pronoun.
The pronoun. Exactly. So
you can save yourself the
hassle or I'm just going
to save myself the hassle.
Okay. So that's about
it for fluency builder.
Let's listen to today's
dialogue one more time
and we'll be back in a
minute to talk about business.
I've had it. I'm done working for a
company that is taking me nowhere.
So what are you going to do? Just quit?
That's exactly what I'm going to do.
I've decided to create
my own company.
I'm going to write up a
business plan, get some investors,
and start working for myself. Have you
ever written off a business plan before?
Well, no. It can't be that hard.
I mean, all you have to
do is explain your business.
How are you going to do things? And
that's it, right? You can be more wrong.
A well-written business
plan will include an
executive summary which
highlights the idea of the
business in two pages
or less. Then you need to
describe your company
with information such as
what type of legal structure it has,
history, etc. Well, that seems easy enough.
Wait, there's more. Then you need to
introducing, describe your goods or services.
What they are and how they're different
from competitors. Then comes the hard part,
a market analysis. You need to investigate
and analyze hundreds of variables.
You need to take into
consideration socio-economic
factors from GDP per
capita to how many children
on average the population
has. All this information
is useful so that you
can move on to your
strategy and implementation
stage where you will
describe in detail how you
will actually execute your idea.
Geez, is that all? Almost.
The most important piece of
information for your investors
will be the financial
analysis. Here you will
calculate and estimate
sales, cash flow and profits.
After all, people will
want to know when they
will begin to see a
return on their investment.
I think I'll just stick to my
old job and save myself
all the hassle of trying
to start up a business.
So it was pretty interesting that he wanted
to quit his job and just set up a business,
but actually many people say
that business plans are unnecessary.
Really? Do these people have lots of
money and they don't need investors?
I think the problem is
that there are many books
out there that give you
clear examples of companies,
fortune 500 companies that
started out without a business plan.
So I think many people
take this as a rule.
Well, they didn't need one or it's
not really necessary or why should I
write up a business
plan? Well, I'm not an
entrepreneur and I'm not
a business person, but my
feeling is that a business
plan is as much for
investors as it is for yourself.
It helps you clarify your goals.
It helps you explain your objectives to
your future colleagues. I think it's just a
really good way to map
out the first year of a
business because it
attempts to want to business
is fail in that first year. So I think it's
a really important step. Yeah, exactly.
So it's very interesting.
We've talked a little bit about
business here, but we
would like to know your
ideas or your comments
or any other suggestions
that you have about this topic
or any topic on EnglishPod.
So why don't you send us a comment or a
personal message. We are at EnglishPod.com
and we'll see you guys there.
Bye, everyone. Bye.